Hello, English learners.
你好，英语学习者。
Welcome back to EnglishPod.
欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And I'm Erika.
我是Erika。
And today we're going to be talking about a really common situation with parents.
今天我们要讨论一个父母常遇到的常见情况。
Yeah, when you're a teenager, you always need to ask your parents for money, ask your parents
是的，当你十几岁时，你总是需要向父母要钱、要车，
for the car, or ask your parents if you can do something.
或者问父母你是否可以做某事。
Exactly.
没错。
And that's what we're going to be looking at is how you can ask for permission for the
我们要看的就是如何请求允许用车、
car, for money.
要钱。
Right.
对。
And these phrases are not only for your parents, right?
这些短语不仅适用于你的父母，对吧？
No, you could use them in your office with your boss or for any situation where you need
不，你可以在办公室对老板使用，或者在任何需要
to ask politely.
礼貌请求的场合。
Yes.
是的。
Okay, so let's take a look at Vocabulary Preview.
好的，那我们来看看词汇预览。
Vocabulary Preview.
词汇预览。
We have one word for you today.
今天我们有一个单词要介绍。
Concerts.
音乐会。
A concert.
一场音乐会。
A concert is an event, right?
音乐会是一个活动，对吧？
Yeah.
是的。
Where people play music.
人们在那里演奏音乐。
Right.
对。
So you have different types of concerts, like a rock concert.
所以有不同类型的音乐会，比如摇滚音乐会。
They play rock music.
他们演奏摇滚乐。
Or a pop concert.
或者流行音乐会。
Yeah, a pop music.
是的，流行音乐。
Or even a classical music concert.
甚至古典音乐会。
Exactly, where you have people playing violins and pianos.
没错，那里有人演奏小提琴和钢琴。
Yeah.
是的。
Okay, concert.
好的，音乐会。
So concerts are always for music.
所以音乐会总是关于音乐的。
Yeah, exactly.
是的，没错。
They're always for music.
它们总是关于音乐的。
Well, with that, let's go into our dialogue.
好了，接下来我们进入对话。
Marco, what happens here?
Marco，这里发生了什么？
Well, basically we have a teenage girl who needs to go to a concert and is asking her
嗯，基本上是一个十几岁的女孩需要去听音乐会，正在问她的
dad for something.
为了某事找爸爸。
All right, let's listen.
好了，我们来听。
Hey, daddy.
嘿，老爸。
You look great today.
你今天看起来很棒。
I like your tie.
我喜欢你的领带。
By the way, I was wondering, can I...
顺便问一下，我在想，能不能……
No.
不行。
I haven't even told you what it is yet.
我还没告诉你是什么事呢。
Okay, okay.
好吧，好吧。
What do you want?
你想要什么？
Do you think I could borrow the car?
你觉得我能借车吗？
I'm going to a concert tonight.
我今晚要去听音乐会。
Um, I don't think so.
嗯，我觉得不行。
I need the car tonight to pick up your mother.
我今晚需要用车去接你妈妈。
Ugh, I told you about it last week.
呃，我上周就跟你说过了。
So you're not going to pick up your mother?
所以你不打算去接你妈妈了？
No, I'm not going to.
不，我不去了。
I'm going to a concert.
我要去听音乐会。
here. The first one, hottest. Hottest. Hottest. So this is the superlative of hot. Right.
这里。第一个，最火辣的。最火辣的。最火辣的。这是hot的最高级。没错。
So the hottest guy in school is... The most handsome... Yeah, the most sexy guy in school.
所以学校里最火辣的男生是……最帅的……对，学校里最性感的男生。
Exactly. So if somebody is hot, they are really attractive. Really good looking. Really good
没错。所以如果说某人hot，就是他们非常有吸引力。非常好看。非常好看。
looking. And so, Marco, is this a word that is only used for men? No, you can also use
那么，Marco，这个词只用于男性吗？不，你也可以用于女性。
it for women. And what about things? You know, recently with Paris Hilton, it's more
那用于事物呢？你知道，最近随着Paris Hilton，这个词更常用于事物，比如，哇，我买了辆新车。哇，真火辣。没错。但我想我们
popular with things like, wow, I got a new car. Wow, that's hot. Right. But I guess we
也许应该告诉我们的听众要小心使用这个词。是的，你最好不要对某人说你很火辣。不，这不礼貌。但和朋友在一起时，你可以
maybe should tell our listeners to be careful with this word. Yeah, you don't really want
用这个词。没错。如果我和朋友聊天，看到一个女孩，哇，她真火辣。好吧。是的，但别告诉她。对，别走到她面前说，哇，你真
to tell somebody you're hot. No. It's not very polite. But with your friends, you can
火辣。好的。下一个词，最受欢迎的。最受欢迎的。最受欢迎的。最受欢迎的。另一个
use this word. Exactly. If I'm talking with my friends and I see a girl like, wow, she's
用这个词。没错。如果我和朋友聊天，看到一个女孩，哇，她真火辣。好吧。是的，但别告诉她。对，别走到她面前说，哇，你真
hot. Okay. Yeah, but just don't tell her. Yeah, don't go up to her and say, wow, you're
火辣。好的。下一个词，最受欢迎的。最受欢迎的。最受欢迎的。最受欢迎的。另一个
hot. Okay. Our next word, most popular. Most popular. Most popular. Most popular. Another
用这个词。没错。如果我和朋友聊天，看到一个女孩，哇，她真火辣。好吧。是的，但别告诉她。对，别走到她面前说，哇，你真
superlative. Exactly. And popular means... Means having a lot of friends. Exactly. Having
最高级。没错。而popular的意思是……就是有很多朋友。没错。有很多朋友。
a lot of friends or being well-known. Or well-liked. Well-liked. Yeah. So in every school, there's
很多朋友或者很有名。或者人缘好。人缘好。对。所以在每所学校里，都有
always like the most popular guy in school, the most popular girl. Yeah. Were you the
总是像学校里最受欢迎的男生、最受欢迎的女生那样。是啊。你当时是那种人吗？
most popular guy? Not really. No, I wasn't the most popular guy, but I wasn't unpopular.
最受欢迎的人？其实不是。不，我不是最受欢迎的人，但也不至于不受欢迎。
Okay. So that's the opposite. Yeah. So I was okay. All right. Our last phrase, fine then.
好的，所以那是反义词。是的，所以我没事。好了，我们最后一个短语，"fine then"。
Fine then. Fine then. Fine then. Well, this is a phrase made up of two simple words, but
好吧。好吧。好吧。嗯，这个短语由两个简单的词组成，但
why don't we listen to some examples so we can understand the meaning of these two words
我们为什么不听一些例子，这样就能理解这两个词的意思了。
together? Example one. Fine then. If you won't go with me, I'll go by myself. Example two.
一起？例一。好吧。如果你不跟我去，我就自己去。例二。
Fine then. If you want to break up, I don't care. Example three. You want to go out with
好吧。如果你想分手，我无所谓。例三。你想和我出去吗？
your friends? Fine then. Go. So you would use this when you agree with somebody, but
你的朋友们？好吧。去吧。所以当你同意某人时，你会用这个，但是
you're not really happy about it. Yeah. It's like saying, I agree, but I'm really angry.
你其实并不高兴。是的。就像在说，我同意，但我很生气。
Right. Maybe sometimes because you don't have a choice. Yeah. Right? Like the girl. Fine
对。也许有时候是因为你别无选择。是的。对吧？就像那个女孩说“好吧”。
then. Yeah. Yeah. So even though we have the word fine in there, it's not really a nice
那好吧。是的。是的。所以尽管里面有“好”这个词，但这不是什么好话。
thing to say to someone. No. No, this is definitely not one to use with your boss. Right. Yeah.
对别人说。不。不，这绝对不适合对你的老板说。对。是的。
Exactly. Okay. Okay. Let's listen to our dialogue again and then we'll talk about some more
没错。好的。好的。我们再听一遍对话，然后讨论更多短语。
phrases. Hey daddy, you look great today. I like your tie. By the way, I was wondering,
嘿，爸爸，你今天看起来很棒。我喜欢你的领带。顺便问一下，我想知道，我能……？
can I? No. I haven't even told you what it is yet. Okay. Okay. What do you want? Do you
不行。我还没告诉你是什么呢。好吧。好吧。你想要什么？你觉得我能借车吗？
think I could borrow the car? I'm going to a concert tonight. I don't think so. I need
我今晚要去听音乐会。我觉得不行。我今晚需要用车去接你妈妈。我上周告诉过你了。
the car tonight to pick up your mother. I told you about it last week. Smelly toes is
臭脚乐队要演出，埃里克问我能不能和他一起去。这个埃里克是谁？拜托，他就像……
playing and Eric asked if I would go with him. Who is this Eric guy? Duh. He's like
他就像……
the hottest and most popular guy at school. Come on dad, please. No can do. Sorry. Fine
学校里最受欢迎最红的男生。拜托了老爸，求你了。不行。抱歉。好吧
then. Would you mind giving me 100 bucks? No way. That's so unfair. There's a lot of
那你能给我100块钱吗？没门。太不公平了。这段对话里有很多
phrases in this dialogue that we can use to ask for something. Right. Exactly. And in
可以用来请求某事的短语。没错。而且
a very polite way. Okay. So we're going to look at three ways of asking for something
是非常礼貌的方式。好的。那我们来看看三种请求方式
and the first way is I was wondering. I was wondering. I was wondering. So I could say
第一种是“我在想”。我在想。我在想。所以我可以这样说
I was wondering, can I borrow your car? Yeah. Or I was wondering, can I stay at your house?
我在想，能借你的车吗？是的。或者我在想，能住在你家吗？
Okay. It's a very nice way to ask something. Yeah. It's like to begin a question. To begin,
好的。这是一种非常礼貌的请求方式。是的。就像开始一个问题。开始，
yeah. All right. Let's take a look at the next one and it's basically the same thing.
是的。好的。我们来看下一个，基本上是一样的。
Do you think I could? Do you think I could? Do you think I could? Do you think I could?
你觉得我能……吗？你觉得我能……吗？你觉得我能……吗？你觉得我能……吗？
Borrow the car? Yeah. Or do you think I could use your computer? I can say I was wondering,
借车？是的。或者你觉得我能用你的电脑吗？我可以说“我在想”，
can I use your computer? Do you think I could use your computer? Yeah. They mean the same.
我能用你的电脑吗？你觉得我可以用你的电脑吗？是的，它们意思一样。
Right. Now let's look at the last one. Would you mind? Would you mind? Would you mind?
对。现在我们来看最后一个。你介意吗？你介意吗？你介意吗？
Would you mind? So I could say, would you mind holding this for me? Yep. Or would you
你介意吗？所以我可以问，你介意帮我拿一下这个吗？嗯。或者你介意
mind finishing this report for me? Now there's an interesting thing here that you have the
帮我完成这份报告吗？这里有个有趣的地方，动词要用
verb in a gerund form, right? Right. The ing form. Exactly. Giving, holding, finishing.
动名词形式，对吧？对。就是ing形式。没错。给、拿、完成。
So we've got I was wondering, can I do something? Right. And would you mind doing something?
所以我们有“我想知道，我能做某事吗？”对。还有“你介意做某事吗？”
Yeah. So you have the ing. Be very, very careful. Be sure to not say, would you mind to give
是的。所以要用ing形式。要非常非常小心。千万不要说“你介意给”
me? Right. That's wrong. Right. That's wrong. Wrong, wrong, wrong. Wrong, wrong, wrong.
我？对，那是错的。对，那是错的。错错错。错错错。
So you would say, would you mind giving me? Yep. Okay. Let's listen to some more examples
所以你要说“你介意给我吗？”嗯。好的。我们来听更多例子
of these three phrases. Example one. Would you mind cooking dinner tonight? I'll be home
关于这三个短语的。例一。你介意今晚做饭吗？我会晚回家。
late. Example two. We were wondering if you could buy the tickets for us. Example three.
晚了。例子二。我们想知道你是否能帮我们买票。例子三。
Do you think you can have those reports finished by today? All right. So I think it's really
你觉得今天能完成那些报告吗？好了。所以我认为这真的很
clear now and it's a very useful way of asking for things. Okay. So let's listen to our dialogue
清楚了，这是一种非常有用的请求方式。好的。那我们再听一遍对话
for the third time and then we'll come back and talk a little bit more. Hey daddy, you
然后回来再聊一会儿。嘿，爸爸，你
look great today. I like your tie. By the way, I was wondering, can I? No. I haven't
今天看起来很棒。我喜欢你的领带。顺便问一下，我想知道，我能……？不。我还没
even told you what it is yet. Okay. Okay. What do you want? Do you think I could borrow
告诉你是什么事呢。好吧。好吧。你想要什么？你觉得我能借
the car? I'm going to a concert tonight. Um, I don't think so. I need the car tonight to
车吗？我今晚要去听音乐会。嗯，我觉得不行。我今晚需要用车去
pick up your mother. I told you about it last week. Smelly toes is playing and Eric asked
接你妈妈。我上周告诉过你。臭脚乐队要演出，埃里克问
if I would go with him. Who is this Eric guy? He's like the hottest and most popular guy
我能不能和他一起去。这个埃里克是谁？他是学校里最火最受欢迎的人
at school. Come on dad, please. No can do. Sorry. Fine then. Would you mind giving me
拜托了，爸爸，求你了。不行。抱歉。那好吧。你介意给我
100 bucks? No way. That's so unfair. So Marco, you said that this dialogue really brought
100块？没门。太不公平了。那么马可，你说这个对话真的让你
back some memories for you. Yeah, my dad was exactly the same way. I would just say dad
想起了很多往事。是啊，我爸爸完全就是这样。我只要一喊爸
and he would be like, no. So he would always cut me off before I ask anything. Sounds like
他就会说不行。所以他总是在我开口之前就打断我。听起来
a pretty strict guy. No, but it was a lot of fun. Sometimes he would just say it just
是个很严厉的人。不，但其实挺有趣的。有时候他这么说只是
to make me angry or something like that. Like just as a joke. Yeah, exactly. But it was
为了让我生气之类的。就像开玩笑一样。对，没错。但是
difficult to get him to lend me the car for example. Really? Oh yeah. I mean he wouldn't
想让他借车给我很难。真的吗？哦是啊。我是说他不会
just lend me the car and sometimes if he did lend me the car, then the next day he would
轻易借车给我，有时候就算他借了，第二天他就会
be like, hey, you need to wash the car or something like that. So you had to pay him
说，嘿，你得洗车或者什么的。所以你得回报他。
back. I had to pay him back with something. In my family, I was always allowed to borrow
我得用什么东西回报他。在我家，我一直都可以借
the car because we lived really, really far away from the city. So there were no buses
车，因为我们住得离城市非常非常远。所以没有公交车
or subway, but I always got to borrow the worst car, you know, the most terrible car.
或者地铁，但我总是得借最差的车，你知道，最糟糕的车。
Which led to so many problems like my car stopping working in the middle of the street,
这导致了很多问题，比如我的车在路中间熄火，
which was never good. We did used to live a little bit further away from downtown, but
这从来都不是好事。我们以前确实住得离市中心稍远一点，但
we had a good bus system. So it would just be like, take the bus, it's cheaper and stuff
我们有很好的公交系统。所以就像，坐公交，更便宜之类的。
like that. So I didn't really get the car that often until I bought my own or until
所以我并不经常用车，直到我自己买了车，或者直到
I had a motorcycle of my own and then problem solved. All right. Well, I want to know from
我有了自己的摩托车，问题才解决。好的。那么，我想问问
our listeners, what did they ask for from their parents? Exactly. Did you ask for the
我们的听众，他们向父母要过什么？没错。你是要
car? Did you ask for money? Or did you ask for a pony? Did you ask for a pony? I had
车吗？还是要钱？或者是要一匹小马？你要过小马吗？我有个
a friend who had a summer home. Really? So he would ask for the keys to the summer home.
朋友有避暑别墅。真的？所以他会要避暑别墅的钥匙。
Okay. Well, come to our website, EnglishPod.com. Exactly. Leave your questions and comments.
好的。那么，请访问我们的网站 EnglishPod.com。没错。留下你的问题和评论。
We want to hear from you. We want to know what you think. And Erica and I are definitely
我们想听听你的意见。我们想知道你的想法。而且我和Erica一定会
there to answer any doubts. All right. Well, guys, thanks for listening and until next
在那里解答任何疑问。好了，各位，感谢收听，下次
time, bye.
再见。